<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>the smaller things</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://smallerthings.org/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://smallerthings.org/</id><updated>2015-08-11T13:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>SciPy 2015: come for the conference, stay for the people</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/2015-scipy.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-08-11T13:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2015-08-11:2015-scipy.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s now been several weeks since I returned from my first &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://scipy2015.scipy.org/"&gt;SciPy&lt;/a&gt;, and I realized I
had yet to actually write about it on my own blog. Well, late is better than
never. If nothing else, the time delay has allowed the dust to settle for a
more coherent post.&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Short version: &lt;strong&gt;SciPy was perhaps the most fun I&amp;#8217;ve had at a&amp;nbsp;conference.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why? Several reasons. First, the audience is very diverse: most are working in
science but many others are working in tech and software development. This is
in contrast to many of the conferences I&amp;#8217;ve attended which are primarily
scientists working in my field, very few of which spend much of their time
developing and maintaining&amp;nbsp;software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the conference itself is different than most in terms of its basic
structure, composed&amp;nbsp;of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 days of&amp;nbsp;tutorials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 days of main&amp;nbsp;conference&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 days of&amp;nbsp;sprints&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this was my first time attending, I decided to get the full SciPy
experience and attend the whole week. I&amp;#8217;m glad I&amp;nbsp;did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two tutorials I most enjoyed were those on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/amueller/scipy_2015_sklearn_tutorial"&gt;machine learning with
scikit-learn&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/chdoig/scipy2015-blaze-bokeh"&gt;using bokeh to create interactive plots&lt;/a&gt;. Although I had
played briefly with both packages before, these sessions offered a more
thorough view to what can be done with them, and most importantly, &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt;.
In particular, for &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://scikit-learn.org/"&gt;scikit-learn&lt;/a&gt; I was struck at how well thought-out
its built-in parameter sweeps and cross-validation machinery was, and it&amp;#8217;s given me
ideas for how to build similar robustness machinery for other packages, e.g.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/projectmesa/mesa"&gt;mesa&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#8217;m not entirely sure yet where I might make use of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bokeh.pydata.org/"&gt;bokeh&lt;/a&gt;, since
ultimately plots I produce need to be exported to a printable form. However,
for publishing data visualizations to the web it&amp;#8217;s a great&amp;nbsp;option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference itself sported three simultaneous tracks of talks, a poster
session, and daily lightning talks. A few of my&amp;nbsp;favorites:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://youtu.be/1kkFZ4P-XHg"&gt;Dask: Out-of-Core Numpy and Pandas through Task Scheduling&lt;/a&gt;: a talk on
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dask.pydata.org/"&gt;dask&lt;/a&gt;, which provides data structures that can do complex out-of-core
operations with an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; similar to numpy and&amp;nbsp;pandas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://youtu.be/nddj5OA8LJo"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HDF5&lt;/span&gt; is Eating the World&lt;/a&gt;: a talk by Andrew Collette (author of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.h5py.org/"&gt;h5py&lt;/a&gt;) on
ways to wield &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HDF5&lt;/span&gt; effectively, as well as exciting new developments in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HDF5&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://youtu.be/TBBtOeY2Q78"&gt;Deep Learning: Tips from the Road&lt;/a&gt;: a talk by Kyle Kastner on deep
learning, its uses, and its limitations. This is a great, short intro to
neural&amp;nbsp;networks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://youtu.be/lcySLoprPMc"&gt;Agent Based Modeling in Python with Mesa&lt;/a&gt;: introduction of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/projectmesa/mesa"&gt;mesa&lt;/a&gt;, a new
package that fills a hole in the python ecosystem: a package for building
agent-based&amp;nbsp;simulations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://youtu.be/_3YoaeoiIFI"&gt;VisPy: Harnessing the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt; for Fast, High Level Visualization&lt;/a&gt;: a great talk
by Luke Campagnola on the capabilities of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://vispy.org/"&gt;VisPy&lt;/a&gt; to generate complex visualizations
in real time using the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt; and&amp;nbsp;OpenGL.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many more where that came from,&amp;nbsp;including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://youtu.be/ZSM-tmbBZ5E"&gt;Time Series Analysis for Network&amp;nbsp;Security&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://youtu.be/TGGGDpb04Yc"&gt;Statistical Thinking for Data&amp;nbsp;Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://youtu.be/X0pAhJgySxk"&gt;xray: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ND&lt;/span&gt; Labeled Arrays and&amp;nbsp;Datasets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://youtu.be/JSFZ3i3WcjQ"&gt;RESTful &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HDF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://youtu.be/OuhtpxGuboY"&gt;Teaching with IPython/Jupyter Notebooks and&amp;nbsp;JupyterHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://youtu.be/eYIPEDnp5C4"&gt;Accelerating Python with the Numba &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JIT&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;Compiler&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each day of the main conference featured a keynote, all three of which are
worth&amp;nbsp;watching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://youtu.be/MNosMXFGtBE"&gt;Data Science at the New York Times by Chris&amp;nbsp;Wiggins&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://youtu.be/kHdkFyGCxiY"&gt;My Data Journey with Python by Wes&amp;nbsp;McKinney&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://youtu.be/5GlNDD7qbP4"&gt;State of the Tools by Jake&amp;nbsp;VanderPlas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it&amp;#8217;s impossible to attend everything, I&amp;#8217;m extremely thankful all of these talks
can be viewed directly on YouTube. Check out the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLYx7XA2nY5Gcpabmu61kKcToLz0FapmHu"&gt;full playlist&lt;/a&gt; for plenty&amp;nbsp;more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last two days featured sprints. For the uninitiated: these are long blocks of time
during which you can work on issues in a codebase collaboratively and in-person
with others. At SciPy, however, mostly these are just a great way to get
involved in new projects and work alongside some of the core developers. I&amp;#8217;m
particularly interested in machine learning applications to simulation work, so
I split my time between working on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://scikit-learn.org/"&gt;scikit-learn&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/projectmesa/mesa"&gt;mesa&lt;/a&gt;. Although I only
ended up submitting a couple PRs to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://scikit-learn.org/"&gt;scikit-learn&lt;/a&gt; over the course of the
weekend, I got a good sense of the structure of the packages and had memorable
discussions with the developers. The only problem now is figuring out where
I&amp;#8217;m going to devote my (rather limited) time outside of graduate school to open
source projects that aren&amp;#8217;t &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mdanalysis.org"&gt;mdanalysis&lt;/a&gt; related. The upside is there are
really no bad&amp;nbsp;choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides all the new tools and technical developments SciPy made me aware of, what I
value most from the conference are the people that I met and the connections I
made with them. The scientific Python community includes some of the most
intelligent and passionate people I&amp;#8217;ve ever met. It was a pleasure to spend a
week with a few of&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="data"></category><category term="science"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="scipy"></category></entry><entry><title>SciPy 2015: Introducing MDSynthesis</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/2015-introducing-mdsynthesis.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-29T23:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2015-06-29:2015-introducing-mdsynthesis.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Although I&amp;#8217;ve announced as much on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/dotsdl/status/598638811581526016"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#8217;m excited to present a poster
talk this year at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.scipy2015.scipy.org"&gt;SciPy&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#8217;ll be my first time attending, and I&amp;#8217;m looking
forward to meeting others that are passionate in advancing science through
software, and in particular with&amp;nbsp;Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll be presenting a software package I&amp;#8217;ve been working on called
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/Becksteinlab/MDSynthesis"&gt;MDSynthesis&lt;/a&gt;, which has vastly improved the way I do science with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Molecular_dynamics"&gt;molecular
dynamics&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MD&lt;/span&gt;) simulations. MDSynthesis addresses an important bottleneck in
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MD&lt;/span&gt; research: going from raw simulation data (perhaps many terabytes, spread
over tens to hundreds of simulations) to information that allows us to answer
biophysical questions. I&amp;#8217;ll&amp;nbsp;explain&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the obstacles to using modern data science tools like &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pandas.pydata.org/"&gt;pandas&lt;/a&gt; to analyze
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MD&lt;/span&gt; data is the multitude of formats the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MD&lt;/span&gt; ecosystem trades in. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.charmm.org/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CHARMM&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ks.uiuc.edu/Research/namd/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NAMD&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; use &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DCD&lt;/span&gt; files, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ambermd.org/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AMBER&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; uses a NetCDF-derived format, and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.gromacs.org/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GROMACS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; uses
an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XDR&lt;/span&gt; format; all told, there are at least 13 different formats used for
storage of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MD&lt;/span&gt; trajectory data, each with unique strengths and limitations.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mdanalysis.org"&gt;MDAnalysis&lt;/a&gt; is a python package that provides a common interface to many of
these formats, turning trajectory data into numpy arrays that can be handled
with the full power of the python&amp;nbsp;universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the diversity in trajectory formats isn&amp;#8217;t the only obstacle to distilling
information from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MD&lt;/span&gt; data; what&amp;#8217;s also a problem is the variety of inputs
available for building any particular simulation system. For example, when
simulating a single protein, I have a lot of choices in: forcefields, starting
conformation, protonation states, solvent, ions, temperature and pressure
algorithm&amp;#8230;the list goes on. The picture becomes more complicated when one
wants to run different types of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MD&lt;/span&gt;, as there are also a wide variety of
enhanced-sampling methods available for&amp;nbsp;use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;#8217;s still not all: trajectory data can take a while to churn through
to extract measures we are interested in, depending on the measure and depending
on the number/length of trajectories. It&amp;#8217;s therefore useful to store intermediate
data so we can interactively explore&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Managing this complexity is burdensome, and frankly, boring. I&amp;#8217;d rather spend
my limited time and energy doing science than managing my ever-growing
collection of data. Furthermore, I want quick, specific, and easy access to the
data I have so that I can begin answering&amp;nbsp;questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MDSynthesis has done this for me. The basic idea behind the package is to
provide persistent objects that serve as data storage units, called
&lt;em&gt;containers&lt;/em&gt;.  One such container is the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mdsynthesis.readthedocs.org/en/master/Sim.html"&gt;Sim&lt;/a&gt; object. This can store any
number of MDAnalysis Universe definitions (topologies + trajectories), along
with atom selections for later use. Sims store their state directly to disk in
a thin &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HDF5&lt;/span&gt; database (using &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.pytables.org/"&gt;PyTables&lt;/a&gt;), allowing recall of the same Sim
instance later, or at the same time in another python session. Most
importantly, Sims give an interface for easily storing pandas and numpy data
structures in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HDF5&lt;/span&gt; format with no fuss, with just as easy recall. Almost any
other python data structure can also be stored just as easily; the container
will pickle what it can&amp;#8217;t serialize to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HDF5&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond Sims, there are also &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mdsynthesis.readthedocs.org/en/master/Group.html"&gt;Groups&lt;/a&gt;, which can store Sims and other Groups as
members for easy recall of whole ensembles of containers and easy aggregation
of their stored&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those are the basic elements; more details can be found in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mdsynthesis.readthedocs.org/en/master/index.html"&gt;docs&lt;/a&gt;. We just
made an alpha release of the package last week which is already usable for
daily work, but the project is still very young. What&amp;#8217;s particularly exciting
for me is that development of the package has already fed back into development
of MDAnalysis, with even more performance and persistence functionality on the&amp;nbsp;way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find this software useful, let me know! If it&amp;#8217;s missing something
that it sorely needs, feel free to submit an &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/Becksteinlab/MDSynthesis/issues"&gt;issue&lt;/a&gt; and we&amp;#8217;ll get
cracking on it. Pull requests are also&amp;nbsp;welcome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="molecular dynamics"></category><category term="data"></category><category term="science"></category></entry><entry><title>Software Carpentry workshop at Oklahoma State University post-mortem</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/2015-software-carpentry-osu-postmortem.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-05-30T18:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2015-05-30:2015-software-carpentry-osu-postmortem.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week I taught my first &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; workshop at Oklahoma State
University. The workshop had been in such demand that we had a total of four
instructors, including &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.jduck.net/"&gt;Jonah Duckles&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://k8hert.blogspot.com/"&gt;Kate Hertweck&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://about.me/timtom"&gt;Thomas Guignard&lt;/a&gt;,
and myself. I arrived at the hotel close to 2am the first day of the workshop,
and was running on nespresso during most of the morning&amp;nbsp;session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though originally Thomas and I were set to teach one room together, due to
flight troubles Jonah took over the session on the Unix shell that kicked
things off. I spent most of the time fixing issues with GitBash (usually
fixed by reinstalling it) and helping people connect to the network (curse
those certificates!), but these issues didn&amp;#8217;t affect most of our learners. I
was able to spend at least a little time watching Jonah teach, too, and
I can say I learned a few things myself (e.g. that &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;tr&lt;/tt&gt; is a&amp;nbsp;thing!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I taught the session on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.python.org"&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, which was split into two parts over the
two days. This decision was made at the cost of omitting &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt; for Day 2. It
worked out well because even though I went too fast the first day (this was
the dominant complaint from feedback), we still only barely touched on
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/06-func.html"&gt;functions&lt;/a&gt; by the end of it. The second day&amp;#8217;s session was entirely filled
by the second half of material, which built on that of the&amp;nbsp;first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was my first time teaching the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWC&lt;/span&gt; Python lesson, and since it&amp;#8217;s become an
indispensable tool for doing my own research, I made use of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ipython.org/"&gt;iPython Notebook&lt;/a&gt;.
To help combat the problem of learners getting behind and needing to see content
that I&amp;#8217;ve since scrolled past, I did all my work out of a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dropbox.com"&gt;Dropbox&lt;/a&gt; folder
and shared a link to my notebook file on the etherpad. Although a good idea, the
biggest problem was that most learners couldn&amp;#8217;t figure out how to view the file,
since downloading and clicking on it usually results in it being opened in a
text editor (they&amp;#8217;re &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JSON&lt;/span&gt; files), leading to more confusion than answers.
What&amp;#8217;s more, it&amp;#8217;s hard for many learners to find their working directory (where
they&amp;#8217;re working in a GitBash / terminal shell session) in the graphical file
manager, so telling them to download the file and move it to the directory
their notebook session is running from results mostly in blank&amp;nbsp;stares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately one of our helpers added the notebook link to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://nbviewer.ipython.org/"&gt;NBViewer&lt;/a&gt;, which
renders the notebook directly in the browser so the students didn&amp;#8217;t need to
bother with the file at all. This required some fiddling to ensure that
NBViewer actually picked up the updates whenever I saved my working notebook,
but otherwise it worked &lt;em&gt;extremely well&lt;/em&gt;. The students very much appreciated
being able to click the nbviewer link in the etherpad and view my entire
running notebook, hitting refresh to see it as it updates. I should note,
however, that the time between me saving and the updated notebook showing up on
refresh was at least a couple minutes; Thomas did some troubleshooting on this
front to try and fix this, but I don&amp;#8217;t think we managed much better than this.
But I&amp;#8217;ll take that over nothing!&amp;nbsp;:D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve since removed the Dropbox share, but &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://nbviewer.ipython.org/gist/dotsdl/c360b1927323667e3c21"&gt;the final notebook can be viewed
here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the session on Day 1, I cleaned up the working notebook. I didn&amp;#8217;t
add anything that wasn&amp;#8217;t discussed in the session, but instead recorded more
of my commentary in the notebook itself since there wasn&amp;#8217;t time to record
it live. The learners appreciated this the next morning, especially with
the NBViewer updates, since they could refer back to what we had done
in case their notebooks were missing things we would need that&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a conscious effort on Day 2 to slooooow doooowwn, and I think I succeeded.
We ended up making it to the goal, which is how to write Python scripts that
behave like shell commands (showing that shell commands are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; magic, and
you, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YES&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YOU&lt;/span&gt;!, can write your own!). The feedback was generally more positive
on this day, and the discussions that followed indicate that people were happy
with what they had spent the time&amp;nbsp;learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas closed out the day with a lesson on Git. Despite it being his first
time teaching that particular lesson (it didn&amp;#8217;t show!), he went at a good pace
and we were able to get through pair-wise collaboration on a publicly hosted
git repository (using &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://github.com"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;). Among the teaching tools
I plan to steal from him is his analogy of commits as group photos. That is,
putting things in the staging area can be thought of as bringing people into
the frame of the photo (and perhaps excluding others), while the commit is
taking the photo itself and then clearing the&amp;nbsp;frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was great to meet and learn from the learners, helpers, and my fellow
instructors. I got the full &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/jduckles/status/603906245989289984"&gt;Oklahoma experience&lt;/a&gt;, too little sleep,
and plenty of ideas for next time. Looking forward to many&amp;nbsp;more!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks especially to our host &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/danabrunson"&gt;Dana Brunson&lt;/a&gt; for putting this&amp;nbsp;together!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="teaching"></category><category term="swc"></category><category term="software"></category></entry><entry><title>Upcoming Software Carpentry workshop at Oklahoma State University</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/2015-software-carpentry-osu.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-05-13T18:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2015-05-13:2015-software-carpentry-osu.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In two weeks from today I&amp;#8217;ll be in Stillwater, Oklahoma, teaching at my first
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; workshop.  The topics
will include learning the basics of a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix_shell"&gt;Unix shell&lt;/a&gt;, programming in &lt;a class="reference external" href="www.python.org"&gt;python&lt;/a&gt;, version control and collaboration with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://git-scm.com/"&gt;git&lt;/a&gt;, and data management with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SQL"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Of these, perhaps &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt; is my weakest area
since I hardly ever have need of it, but it&amp;#8217;s a good excuse to brush up! Don&amp;#8217;t
worry folks: I doubt that will be one of the topics I&amp;#8217;ll be the lead
instructor on. I&amp;#8217;m very excited to teach any of the others.&amp;nbsp;:D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing the skillsets and tools with the researchers whose work can benefit
the most from them is why I got involved with Software Carpentry, and I&amp;#8217;m
excited to finally start contributing to this effort. I plan to share my
preparation and post-mortem (is &lt;em&gt;debriefing&lt;/em&gt; a better word?), so watch this
space in the coming&amp;nbsp;weeks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="teaching"></category><category term="swc"></category><category term="software"></category></entry><entry><title>I’m now a Software Carpentry Instructor!</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/2015-software-carpentry-instructor.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-03-25T10:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2015-03-25:2015-software-carpentry-instructor.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back in January I had the privilege to attend an in-person &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; instructor training in Davis, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CA&lt;/span&gt;, hosted by
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/"&gt;Titus Brown&lt;/a&gt;. Software Carpentry is a
non-profit volunteer organization that puts on &amp;#8220;bootcamps&amp;#8221; at institutions all
over the world teaching best practices for building software to do science
efficiently. The three-day training helped to improve my own awareness of how
people learn the technical skills we teach, and I learned plenty about my own
teaching habits (good and bad). I also met many great people doing awesome work
in the open science community. It was well-worth the couch crashing and braving
the cold (Arizona weather makes you a&amp;nbsp;wuss).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, I gave a five-minute lightning lesson as an introduction to Python
to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://third-bit.com/"&gt;Greg Wilson&lt;/a&gt;, completing the final requirement
for becoming an instructor. I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to teaching bootcamps here at
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ASU&lt;/span&gt; this year and next, and hopefully getting out a bit to teach some elsewhere
in the country. I also hope to contribute to the efforts of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://datacarpentry.org/"&gt;Data Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; with material specific to working with molecular
dynamics data. I&amp;#8217;d be keen to discuss this topic with anyone else who&amp;#8217;s
interested. There&amp;#8217;s a lot that could be done on this&amp;nbsp;front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="teaching"></category><category term="swc"></category><category term="software"></category></entry><entry><title>Bumming around Baltimore; or, the Biophysical Society Annual Meeting 2015</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/2015-biophysical-society-annual-meeting.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-02-11T22:45:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2015-02-11:2015-biophysical-society-annual-meeting.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s been a while since I last wrote a blog post, and this is for a couple
(very good) reasons. First, I&amp;#8217;ve been hard at work on a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://github.com/dotsdl/MDSynthesis"&gt;software package for
making molecular dynamics data exploration more manageable&lt;/a&gt;. More on that in another post to
come soon. Second, I had a major conference to prepare for, this being the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.biophysics.org/2015meeting"&gt;Biophysical Society Annual Meeting in Baltimore&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gave a talk at this meeting about our recent work on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1085/jgp.201411219"&gt;sodium proton
antiporters&lt;/a&gt;. The talk was
well-received and the questions allowed me to clarify details that I probably
flew through during the 12 minutes I had to speak. I&amp;#8217;m very happy to have
had the opportunity to share my work to a full&amp;nbsp;room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the talk was a success, for me this last week was more a personal test
in how quickly I can produce new data and distill useful information from it. I
spent a significant amount of time over winter break and the first bit of
January restructuring my workflow, and I am now significantly faster at this.
It isn&amp;#8217;t just pipeline, either; the new approach allows me to effectively
explore my data to generate new inferences and quickly test&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example: I discovered what would become a key element of my talk on
Saturday night, and I gave that talk on Monday. It was a bit too much like
playing with fire than I&amp;#8217;d like to risk in future meetings, but it was
well-worth it this time. The fast turn-around itself is encouraging, since it&amp;#8217;s
looking to be an indication of a very productive&amp;nbsp;year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meeting also brought me in contact with a host of great peers (and giants)
in the community. I&amp;#8217;m glad I got to meet the faces to so many names in such
a short period of time. I had great discussions and made new&amp;nbsp;friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll be spending the next few days relaxing in D.C., but I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to
getting back to the lab. Plenty of fresh ideas to work with in the coming year.
Despite being physically exhausted, I am very pleased with my time in&amp;nbsp;Baltimore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="conferences"></category><category term="talks"></category></entry><entry><title>From Wordpress to Pelican</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/from-wordpress-to-pelican.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-12-26T22:15:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2014-12-26:from-wordpress-to-pelican.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back in September I decided to begin sharing some of my thoughts on science,
software, and education by blogging regularly on my exploits. I&amp;#8217;d previously
built a website on top of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://wordpress.org/"&gt;Wordpress&lt;/a&gt; for
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sundial.physics.asu.edu"&gt;Sundial&lt;/a&gt;, so I decided to go with that
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CMS&lt;/span&gt;. I purchased a domain name through &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.godaddy.com/"&gt;GoDaddy&lt;/a&gt;,
and out of convenience purchased Wordpress hosting through them as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wordpress is a fine &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CMS&lt;/span&gt;, but I despised writing in the built-in editor. I&amp;#8217;m
a vim nerd, and really wanted to write in plaintext in my editor of choice.
Also, I wanted to start sharing code snippets and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ipython.org/notebook.html"&gt;iPython notebooks&lt;/a&gt;, and Wordpress was appearing an awkward
choice at best for&amp;nbsp;this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;pelican&lt;/a&gt;, a static site generator
written in Python that uses ReStructuredText as the markup of choice
for articles. It took a little time to set up, but most of this was
spent trying to approximate my old blog&amp;#8217;s look by way of a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/dotsdl/pelican-bluemoon"&gt;custom theme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re interested in blogging with a statically-generated site through
pelican, start by installing the python module locally with&amp;nbsp;pip:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
pip install --user pelican
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then build a skeleton that includes everything you need to get started&amp;nbsp;with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
pelican-quickstart
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://docs.getpelican.com/"&gt;pelican docs&lt;/a&gt; have up-to-date information
on how to&amp;nbsp;proceed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since pelican generates static html files, they can be cheaply hosted. In fact,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; provides free page hosting via &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;. I created a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/dotsdl/dotsdl.github.io"&gt;repository for my site&lt;/a&gt; and edited the Makefile included
in my pelican project directory to point to it. This allows me to regenerate
and publish my static site&amp;nbsp;with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
make github
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn&amp;#8217;t get much easier. I&amp;#8217;m very&amp;nbsp;pleased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EDIT&lt;/span&gt;: I have added my &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/dotsdl/smallerthings"&gt;blog source to GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. Perhaps if you&amp;#8217;re having trouble
getting something working it will be of&amp;nbsp;help.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="blogging"></category><category term="pelican"></category><category term="wordpress"></category></entry><entry><title>Attempting to be open in a (mostly) closed field</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/open-in-a-closed-field.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-12-26T16:23:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2014-12-26:open-in-a-closed-field.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been following &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/"&gt;Titus Brown&amp;#8217;s blog&lt;/a&gt; for a
little while now, and this blog is part of an effort to emulate his
(&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/blog-practicing-open-science.html"&gt;relatively conservative&lt;/a&gt;)
brand of open science. However, if it wasn&amp;#8217;t obvious from my lack of new content over
the past few months, I&amp;#8217;ve been in a bit of a rut. What&amp;nbsp;gives?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, for one thing I don&amp;#8217;t &amp;#8220;own&amp;#8221; the research I produce. Or, at the very
least, I don&amp;#8217;t &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; own it. There are my collaborators to think about,
not to mention my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PI&lt;/span&gt;, whose ultimate permission I must obtain to openly
discuss the things we are hammering on. And in a competitive field, there is
the real fear (valid? I&amp;#8217;m not sure) of being&amp;nbsp;scooped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what to do? I think the landscape science operates in is changing, and the way science
is done &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; change in order to cope. Funding is becoming &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nature.com/nmeth/journal/v11/n11/full/nmeth.3171.html"&gt;harder to get&lt;/a&gt;.
Reproducing scientific work, even those dependent on software alone, is
difficult. And these days obtaining data is becoming less of a problem; instead,
in many fields the emerging problem is how to cope with data glut, which itself
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jakevdp.github.io/blog/2014/08/22/hacking-academia/"&gt;requires a new skill set&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The open science movement seeks in part to take the lessons from the open source
software movement and apply them to science. This is particularly salient for someone
in my field, since in simulation-based work raw and distilled data is both generated
by software. Open science finds little contradiction&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the more competitive a field is, the more perceived incentive there is to keep
work bottled up until the &lt;em&gt;big reveal&lt;/em&gt; in the form of a journal publication. Rarely
this publication includes the full data set (in my field, this would mean raw simulation
trajectories and the input parameters) and all code (mainly analysis code, though
not all molecular dynamics codes are open source). What&amp;#8217;s more, the main input
to our simulations are experimental structures, and the crystallography community
is known to be &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; competitive. We are thus constrained by our experimentalist
collaborators&amp;#8217;&amp;nbsp;needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anything, I&amp;#8217;ll be using this space to share what I can about my work, especially
ideas with regard to software and scalable analysis (with a bent toward applications
to molecular dynamics problems). Change in science is slow, but I&amp;#8217;ll try to do my
part&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="openaccess"></category><category term="open science"></category></entry><entry><title>Paywalls and lost knowledge</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/paywalls-and-lost-knowledge.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-10-16T05:21:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2014-10-16:paywalls-and-lost-knowledge.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s taken me a while, but I now have a system for keeping up with
(however poorly) the exponentially growing scientific literature. I&amp;#8217;ll
expound more on my method of choice in another post, but no matter how
fast I try to get at processing papers, new and old, one thing disrupts
my flow more than any other:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paywall"&gt;paywalls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every scientist knows them well. You&amp;#8217;re reading papers, and you see a
detail that piques your curiosity enough to check the reference. You
then type as much of the title as you care to into Google and click on
the first link that looks like it might have a manuscript behind it. Oh
no, it&amp;#8217;s just &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed"&gt;Pubmed&lt;/a&gt;. But it
has links to the full text!&amp;nbsp;Click.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quickly you scan for a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; download link. But there&amp;#8217;s a number next to
it. &lt;strong&gt;For the low, low price of $28.00, this article could be yours!&lt;/strong&gt;
Or you could &amp;#8220;rent&amp;#8221; it for $4.00, whatever that&amp;nbsp;means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have roughly 400 articles in my Zotero library, and it&amp;#8217;s growing fast.
Luckily I&amp;#8217;m privileged to have access to
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lib.asu.edu/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ASU&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8216;s library subscriptions for most (though
certainly not all) journals, but this requires me to engage in further
gymnastics to use the proxy server to get&amp;nbsp;access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time I&amp;#8217;ve pulled an article (or more likely several) into my
library, I&amp;#8217;ve forgotten the context of why I cared to find it&amp;nbsp;in the
first place. I may have jotted down a note or two, but the full moment
is lost, possibly forever. What&amp;#8217;s worse, though I may be able to scrap
most of my thoughts back together and carry on with chasing the rabbit
down the idea hole, imagine being a student at a smaller university with
a less-endowed library. That idea that led to the chase may never find
what it needs to bother&amp;nbsp;pursuing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every paywall represents an opportunity lost, if not several. They are
plaque in the arteries of science, slowing down everyone. Luckily the
scene is changing with the efforts of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_access"&gt;open access
movement&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#8217;s certainly&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="openaccess"></category></entry><entry><title>Software Carpentry @ ASU</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/software-carpentry-asu.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-09-29T04:54:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2014-09-29:software-carpentry-asu.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://smallerthings.org/2014/09/software-carpentry-bootcamp-asu/"&gt;previous
post&lt;/a&gt;,
this weekend I participated in my first &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software
Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;bootcamp. I had the
pleasure of meeting the instructors and all the other helpers involved
on Friday&amp;nbsp;over pizza and beer, and in particular spent considerable time
nerding out with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://naupaka.net/"&gt;Naupaka&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;over all things vim
and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://vita.had.co.nz/papers/tidy-data.pdf"&gt;tidy data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Day 1, the topic of the morning was
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.r-project.org/"&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;. From what I understand, it was only
recently that Software Carpentry decided to add R to their curriculum.
Though I certainly learned plenty myself as I rushed about helping
participants through small problems, there is a lot of good stuff (and
plenty of potential)&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R is an analysis tool first and a programming language second. This
makes it a pragmatic choice for researchers but still a difficult one to
teach. We used&amp;nbsp;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.rstudio.com/"&gt;RStudio&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;as the
environment for introducing things, and this may have taken the edge off
for the command-line averse. I didn&amp;#8217;t get a chance to follow along with
the exercises too much myself, but I&amp;#8217;m particularly interested in
learning more about the use of factors. If anyone has any resources for
understanding what factors are, why they are useful, etc., I&amp;#8217;d love to
hear about&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That afternoon we switched topics to the shell, or more specifically
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.gnu.org/software/bash/"&gt;bash&lt;/a&gt;. The session started well
enough, but given a distribution of participants that ranged from zero
experience to intermediate, it proved difficult to please everyone.
Also, as a note to anyone that does a bootcamp on the shell (or even any
topic): &lt;em&gt;give a motivation behind everything you demonstrate, both in
broad and immediate scope&lt;/em&gt;. Although it can be obvious why a given trick
is useful to an experienced user, the novice can often be left wondering
what benefit this has compared to what they already do to get work done.
This is especially true for the shell, since 90% of work done in the
shell is moving around a file system, which most scientists already
accomplish by clicking around a file browser. People have to see a clear
advantage to adopt new&amp;nbsp;practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day 2 (today) started off with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://git-scm.com/"&gt;git&lt;/a&gt;. The
instructors did well to put extensive focus on giving motivation for
git&amp;#8217;s use, given the feedback from the previous day&amp;#8217;s session on the
shell. This was especially important for git, since for many scientists
it is considered to be non-essential in the toolbox of software things.
Software Carpentry hopes to change&amp;nbsp;this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist: &lt;strong&gt;git is great for more than just code.&lt;/strong&gt; Though originally
produced to address the needs of the software community, as a version
control system git works particularly well for paper writing, alone or
with collaborators. And even though git is optimal when working with
text-only files, it is perfectly happy to store away&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;anything&lt;/strong&gt; you
like and version control it.&amp;nbsp;Further, pushing the materials used to
build a manuscript to a public repository host like
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;is a great way to address the
well-acknowledged problem of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nature.com/news/announcement-reducing-our-irreproducibility-1.12852"&gt;reproducibility in
science&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the afternoon we turned our focus to
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SQL"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, using
an&amp;nbsp;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sqlite.org/"&gt;SQLite&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;database as our toy case for
running queries against. I was running out of steam by about this point,
and I mainly focused on helping the folks on Windows to get sqlite3
working under &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://msysgit.github.io/"&gt;Git Bash&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;(not hard, but
for beginners running around the filesystem is an expensive&amp;nbsp;operation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I&amp;#8217;m happy I got to help put this on and I hope to be involved
in a growing &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SC&lt;/span&gt; community here at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ASU&lt;/span&gt; in the very near future. Assuming
space is still available, I&amp;#8217;m also hoping to attend &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/2014-davis-swc-training.html"&gt;Titus Brown&amp;#8217;s
instructor training in Davis this coming
January&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everyone involved! Looking forward to&amp;nbsp;more!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="bash"></category><category term="git"></category><category term="R"></category><category term="Software Carpentry"></category><category term="SQL"></category></entry><entry><title>Creationism’s beef with scientific theory</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/creationisms-beef-with-scientific-theory.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-09-25T20:48:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2014-09-25:creationisms-beef-with-scientific-theory.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post was originally posted to Facebook. It was a&amp;nbsp;response to a
creationist friend who posted a video of another creationist attempting
to discredit the usual set of scientific theories. I felt I should share
it for others because I&amp;#8217;m terminally optimistic, and I needed the&amp;nbsp;outlet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One&amp;nbsp;recurring mistake made by creationists when trying to discredit
science is this: it is assumed that science must observe &lt;strong&gt;every&lt;/strong&gt;
phenomenon a theory posits to take place in order for that theory to be
considered valid. When a creationist says repeatedly that &amp;#8220;there is no
evidence for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THEORY&lt;/span&gt; X&amp;#8221;, he is oftentimes operating on his standard that
&lt;strong&gt;every&lt;/strong&gt; prediction of that theory must be tested. This is unreasonable
for science to progress; worse, it&amp;#8217;s shown itself to be &lt;strong&gt;unnecessary&lt;/strong&gt;.
The value of theory is that it is better than a library of observations;
it gives greater insight into what&amp;#8217;s actually&amp;nbsp;happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use an analogy: many of my students in an introductory physics course
spent&amp;nbsp;the beginning of the semester doing physics problems with
arithmetic. They were literally throwing numbers around in ways that
&amp;#8220;made sense&amp;#8221; to them until they arrived at an (often wrong) answer.&amp;nbsp;To
break them of this, I began asking questions that required some higher
level thought. Instead of &amp;#8220;how high on the wall does the projectile
strike&amp;#8221; given some set of initial conditions, I asked &amp;#8220;what is the
minimum speed with which the projectile must be fired in order to go
over the wall.&amp;#8221; Those that tried arithmetic quickly realized they&amp;#8217;d have
to trial-and-error it to get the answer, which would be&amp;nbsp;silly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ones that solved the problem instead used the theory they had
learned in class (2D kinematics, a purely descriptive part of classical
mechanics), algebraically finding the speed I asked for. I then asked
them how this speed changes with firing distance, and they could answer
this question by looking at the symbolic answer. I even asked them how
quickly this speed changes with a change in firing angle, effectively
requiring a&amp;nbsp;derivative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When creationists demand evidence for every single facet or prediction
of a theory, they are demanding that science do the arithmetic&amp;#8230;&lt;strong&gt;for
every variation of the problem the theory is addressing&lt;/strong&gt;. This is
unreasonable. Worse, it doesn&amp;#8217;t really tell us much more information
about the set of phenomena we are addressing, just like solving the same
problem over and over again with different numbers doesn&amp;#8217;t really give
insight into what&amp;#8217;s actually&amp;nbsp;happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a finite number of scientists working on a much larger set of
problems (and growing, as we are able to probe more and more of nature),
our limited resources are better spent proving the principles and then
moving on, using those principles to discover ever more. Quantum
mechanics has probably less direct evidence for it than biological
evolution, but we didn&amp;#8217;t waste time endlessly testing every boring case
the theory presents. Instead, we took advantage of it to build materials
that now allow the computer you are using to post emoticons on&amp;nbsp;Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, thank a theory&amp;#8230;or something. And have a nice&amp;nbsp;evening.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Upcoming Software Carpentry bootcamp @ ASU</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/software-carpentry-bootcamp-asu.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-09-23T23:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2014-09-23:software-carpentry-bootcamp-asu.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This weekend (September 26 &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; 27), I will be partaking in my first
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;bootcamp, held
right here at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ASU&lt;/span&gt;. I will be helping with some of the sessions myself,
but otherwise I look forward to learning some R and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt; skills with some
like-minded&amp;nbsp;peers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the uninitiated, Software Carpentry is an organization that actively
works to improve the computational, programming, and data analysis
skills of scientists. This is more than necessary, because though
science often pushes the boundaries of what computing can accomplish,
good software practices are relatively rare among scientists. Version
control, code readability, and software design is becoming increasingly
important as the complexity of computational science&amp;nbsp;increases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll post about my experiences after having attended the two-day
bootcamp. If you are interested in attending yourself, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://naupaka.github.io/2014-09-27-asu/"&gt;register
here&lt;/a&gt;. It should be a good&amp;nbsp;time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Ahoy there!</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/ahoy-there.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-09-22T00:02:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2014-09-22:ahoy-there.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The last time I tried keeping a blog was when I was around 20 years old,
and the topics of the day were mainly of&amp;nbsp;interest to only 20-year-old
me. I was just coming out as gay, learning to deal with feelings I
didn&amp;#8217;t understand. I spent a lot of time thinking about religion, and
plenty of time arguing about it with others. I didn&amp;#8217;t know much about
the world, but I was trying&amp;nbsp;learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m now 25, and in my fourth year of graduate school. I am invested in
my research (plenty to write about on that soon), and I am in a stable
and fulfilling relationship. Grad school started out (very) rough, but
I&amp;#8217;ve found my niche. I&amp;#8217;m generally&amp;nbsp;pleased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided it was appropriate to start sharing my thoughts and
experiences with others. It&amp;#8217;s not something I&amp;#8217;m used to, so it may take
a post or two before I&amp;#8217;ve found&amp;nbsp;my groove. Some posts will be about
science (both content and sociology thereof) and software development;
others will chronicle my teaching and thoughts on the state of
education. Yet others will be personal updates. I think there is space
for all of this&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plenty to&amp;nbsp;come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry></feed>