<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>the smaller things</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://smallerthings.org/feeds/education.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://smallerthings.org/</id><updated>2015-05-30T18:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Software Carpentry workshop at Oklahoma State University post-mortem</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/2015-software-carpentry-osu-postmortem.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-05-30T18:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2015-05-30:2015-software-carpentry-osu-postmortem.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week I taught my first &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; workshop at Oklahoma State
University. The workshop had been in such demand that we had a total of four
instructors, including &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.jduck.net/"&gt;Jonah Duckles&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://k8hert.blogspot.com/"&gt;Kate Hertweck&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://about.me/timtom"&gt;Thomas Guignard&lt;/a&gt;,
and myself. I arrived at the hotel close to 2am the first day of the workshop,
and was running on nespresso during most of the morning&amp;nbsp;session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though originally Thomas and I were set to teach one room together, due to
flight troubles Jonah took over the session on the Unix shell that kicked
things off. I spent most of the time fixing issues with GitBash (usually
fixed by reinstalling it) and helping people connect to the network (curse
those certificates!), but these issues didn&amp;#8217;t affect most of our learners. I
was able to spend at least a little time watching Jonah teach, too, and
I can say I learned a few things myself (e.g. that &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;tr&lt;/tt&gt; is a&amp;nbsp;thing!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I taught the session on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.python.org"&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, which was split into two parts over the
two days. This decision was made at the cost of omitting &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt; for Day 2. It
worked out well because even though I went too fast the first day (this was
the dominant complaint from feedback), we still only barely touched on
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/06-func.html"&gt;functions&lt;/a&gt; by the end of it. The second day&amp;#8217;s session was entirely filled
by the second half of material, which built on that of the&amp;nbsp;first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was my first time teaching the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWC&lt;/span&gt; Python lesson, and since it&amp;#8217;s become an
indispensable tool for doing my own research, I made use of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ipython.org/"&gt;iPython Notebook&lt;/a&gt;.
To help combat the problem of learners getting behind and needing to see content
that I&amp;#8217;ve since scrolled past, I did all my work out of a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dropbox.com"&gt;Dropbox&lt;/a&gt; folder
and shared a link to my notebook file on the etherpad. Although a good idea, the
biggest problem was that most learners couldn&amp;#8217;t figure out how to view the file,
since downloading and clicking on it usually results in it being opened in a
text editor (they&amp;#8217;re &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JSON&lt;/span&gt; files), leading to more confusion than answers.
What&amp;#8217;s more, it&amp;#8217;s hard for many learners to find their working directory (where
they&amp;#8217;re working in a GitBash / terminal shell session) in the graphical file
manager, so telling them to download the file and move it to the directory
their notebook session is running from results mostly in blank&amp;nbsp;stares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately one of our helpers added the notebook link to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://nbviewer.ipython.org/"&gt;NBViewer&lt;/a&gt;, which
renders the notebook directly in the browser so the students didn&amp;#8217;t need to
bother with the file at all. This required some fiddling to ensure that
NBViewer actually picked up the updates whenever I saved my working notebook,
but otherwise it worked &lt;em&gt;extremely well&lt;/em&gt;. The students very much appreciated
being able to click the nbviewer link in the etherpad and view my entire
running notebook, hitting refresh to see it as it updates. I should note,
however, that the time between me saving and the updated notebook showing up on
refresh was at least a couple minutes; Thomas did some troubleshooting on this
front to try and fix this, but I don&amp;#8217;t think we managed much better than this.
But I&amp;#8217;ll take that over nothing!&amp;nbsp;:D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve since removed the Dropbox share, but &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://nbviewer.ipython.org/gist/dotsdl/c360b1927323667e3c21"&gt;the final notebook can be viewed
here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the session on Day 1, I cleaned up the working notebook. I didn&amp;#8217;t
add anything that wasn&amp;#8217;t discussed in the session, but instead recorded more
of my commentary in the notebook itself since there wasn&amp;#8217;t time to record
it live. The learners appreciated this the next morning, especially with
the NBViewer updates, since they could refer back to what we had done
in case their notebooks were missing things we would need that&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a conscious effort on Day 2 to slooooow doooowwn, and I think I succeeded.
We ended up making it to the goal, which is how to write Python scripts that
behave like shell commands (showing that shell commands are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; magic, and
you, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YES&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YOU&lt;/span&gt;!, can write your own!). The feedback was generally more positive
on this day, and the discussions that followed indicate that people were happy
with what they had spent the time&amp;nbsp;learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas closed out the day with a lesson on Git. Despite it being his first
time teaching that particular lesson (it didn&amp;#8217;t show!), he went at a good pace
and we were able to get through pair-wise collaboration on a publicly hosted
git repository (using &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://github.com"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;). Among the teaching tools
I plan to steal from him is his analogy of commits as group photos. That is,
putting things in the staging area can be thought of as bringing people into
the frame of the photo (and perhaps excluding others), while the commit is
taking the photo itself and then clearing the&amp;nbsp;frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was great to meet and learn from the learners, helpers, and my fellow
instructors. I got the full &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/jduckles/status/603906245989289984"&gt;Oklahoma experience&lt;/a&gt;, too little sleep,
and plenty of ideas for next time. Looking forward to many&amp;nbsp;more!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks especially to our host &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/danabrunson"&gt;Dana Brunson&lt;/a&gt; for putting this&amp;nbsp;together!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="teaching"></category><category term="swc"></category><category term="software"></category></entry><entry><title>Upcoming Software Carpentry workshop at Oklahoma State University</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/2015-software-carpentry-osu.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-05-13T18:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2015-05-13:2015-software-carpentry-osu.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In two weeks from today I&amp;#8217;ll be in Stillwater, Oklahoma, teaching at my first
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; workshop.  The topics
will include learning the basics of a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix_shell"&gt;Unix shell&lt;/a&gt;, programming in &lt;a class="reference external" href="www.python.org"&gt;python&lt;/a&gt;, version control and collaboration with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://git-scm.com/"&gt;git&lt;/a&gt;, and data management with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SQL"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Of these, perhaps &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt; is my weakest area
since I hardly ever have need of it, but it&amp;#8217;s a good excuse to brush up! Don&amp;#8217;t
worry folks: I doubt that will be one of the topics I&amp;#8217;ll be the lead
instructor on. I&amp;#8217;m very excited to teach any of the others.&amp;nbsp;:D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing the skillsets and tools with the researchers whose work can benefit
the most from them is why I got involved with Software Carpentry, and I&amp;#8217;m
excited to finally start contributing to this effort. I plan to share my
preparation and post-mortem (is &lt;em&gt;debriefing&lt;/em&gt; a better word?), so watch this
space in the coming&amp;nbsp;weeks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="teaching"></category><category term="swc"></category><category term="software"></category></entry><entry><title>I’m now a Software Carpentry Instructor!</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/2015-software-carpentry-instructor.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-03-25T10:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2015-03-25:2015-software-carpentry-instructor.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back in January I had the privilege to attend an in-person &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; instructor training in Davis, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CA&lt;/span&gt;, hosted by
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/"&gt;Titus Brown&lt;/a&gt;. Software Carpentry is a
non-profit volunteer organization that puts on &amp;#8220;bootcamps&amp;#8221; at institutions all
over the world teaching best practices for building software to do science
efficiently. The three-day training helped to improve my own awareness of how
people learn the technical skills we teach, and I learned plenty about my own
teaching habits (good and bad). I also met many great people doing awesome work
in the open science community. It was well-worth the couch crashing and braving
the cold (Arizona weather makes you a&amp;nbsp;wuss).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, I gave a five-minute lightning lesson as an introduction to Python
to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://third-bit.com/"&gt;Greg Wilson&lt;/a&gt;, completing the final requirement
for becoming an instructor. I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to teaching bootcamps here at
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ASU&lt;/span&gt; this year and next, and hopefully getting out a bit to teach some elsewhere
in the country. I also hope to contribute to the efforts of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://datacarpentry.org/"&gt;Data Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; with material specific to working with molecular
dynamics data. I&amp;#8217;d be keen to discuss this topic with anyone else who&amp;#8217;s
interested. There&amp;#8217;s a lot that could be done on this&amp;nbsp;front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="teaching"></category><category term="swc"></category><category term="software"></category></entry><entry><title>Software Carpentry @ ASU</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/software-carpentry-asu.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-09-29T04:54:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2014-09-29:software-carpentry-asu.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://smallerthings.org/2014/09/software-carpentry-bootcamp-asu/"&gt;previous
post&lt;/a&gt;,
this weekend I participated in my first &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software
Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;bootcamp. I had the
pleasure of meeting the instructors and all the other helpers involved
on Friday&amp;nbsp;over pizza and beer, and in particular spent considerable time
nerding out with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://naupaka.net/"&gt;Naupaka&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;over all things vim
and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://vita.had.co.nz/papers/tidy-data.pdf"&gt;tidy data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Day 1, the topic of the morning was
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.r-project.org/"&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;. From what I understand, it was only
recently that Software Carpentry decided to add R to their curriculum.
Though I certainly learned plenty myself as I rushed about helping
participants through small problems, there is a lot of good stuff (and
plenty of potential)&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R is an analysis tool first and a programming language second. This
makes it a pragmatic choice for researchers but still a difficult one to
teach. We used&amp;nbsp;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.rstudio.com/"&gt;RStudio&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;as the
environment for introducing things, and this may have taken the edge off
for the command-line averse. I didn&amp;#8217;t get a chance to follow along with
the exercises too much myself, but I&amp;#8217;m particularly interested in
learning more about the use of factors. If anyone has any resources for
understanding what factors are, why they are useful, etc., I&amp;#8217;d love to
hear about&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That afternoon we switched topics to the shell, or more specifically
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.gnu.org/software/bash/"&gt;bash&lt;/a&gt;. The session started well
enough, but given a distribution of participants that ranged from zero
experience to intermediate, it proved difficult to please everyone.
Also, as a note to anyone that does a bootcamp on the shell (or even any
topic): &lt;em&gt;give a motivation behind everything you demonstrate, both in
broad and immediate scope&lt;/em&gt;. Although it can be obvious why a given trick
is useful to an experienced user, the novice can often be left wondering
what benefit this has compared to what they already do to get work done.
This is especially true for the shell, since 90% of work done in the
shell is moving around a file system, which most scientists already
accomplish by clicking around a file browser. People have to see a clear
advantage to adopt new&amp;nbsp;practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day 2 (today) started off with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://git-scm.com/"&gt;git&lt;/a&gt;. The
instructors did well to put extensive focus on giving motivation for
git&amp;#8217;s use, given the feedback from the previous day&amp;#8217;s session on the
shell. This was especially important for git, since for many scientists
it is considered to be non-essential in the toolbox of software things.
Software Carpentry hopes to change&amp;nbsp;this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist: &lt;strong&gt;git is great for more than just code.&lt;/strong&gt; Though originally
produced to address the needs of the software community, as a version
control system git works particularly well for paper writing, alone or
with collaborators. And even though git is optimal when working with
text-only files, it is perfectly happy to store away&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;anything&lt;/strong&gt; you
like and version control it.&amp;nbsp;Further, pushing the materials used to
build a manuscript to a public repository host like
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;is a great way to address the
well-acknowledged problem of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nature.com/news/announcement-reducing-our-irreproducibility-1.12852"&gt;reproducibility in
science&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the afternoon we turned our focus to
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SQL"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, using
an&amp;nbsp;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sqlite.org/"&gt;SQLite&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;database as our toy case for
running queries against. I was running out of steam by about this point,
and I mainly focused on helping the folks on Windows to get sqlite3
working under &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://msysgit.github.io/"&gt;Git Bash&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;(not hard, but
for beginners running around the filesystem is an expensive&amp;nbsp;operation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I&amp;#8217;m happy I got to help put this on and I hope to be involved
in a growing &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SC&lt;/span&gt; community here at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ASU&lt;/span&gt; in the very near future. Assuming
space is still available, I&amp;#8217;m also hoping to attend &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/2014-davis-swc-training.html"&gt;Titus Brown&amp;#8217;s
instructor training in Davis this coming
January&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everyone involved! Looking forward to&amp;nbsp;more!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="bash"></category><category term="git"></category><category term="R"></category><category term="Software Carpentry"></category><category term="SQL"></category></entry><entry><title>Upcoming Software Carpentry bootcamp @ ASU</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/software-carpentry-bootcamp-asu.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-09-23T23:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2014-09-23:software-carpentry-bootcamp-asu.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This weekend (September 26 &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; 27), I will be partaking in my first
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;bootcamp, held
right here at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ASU&lt;/span&gt;. I will be helping with some of the sessions myself,
but otherwise I look forward to learning some R and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt; skills with some
like-minded&amp;nbsp;peers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the uninitiated, Software Carpentry is an organization that actively
works to improve the computational, programming, and data analysis
skills of scientists. This is more than necessary, because though
science often pushes the boundaries of what computing can accomplish,
good software practices are relatively rare among scientists. Version
control, code readability, and software design is becoming increasingly
important as the complexity of computational science&amp;nbsp;increases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll post about my experiences after having attended the two-day
bootcamp. If you are interested in attending yourself, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://naupaka.github.io/2014-09-27-asu/"&gt;register
here&lt;/a&gt;. It should be a good&amp;nbsp;time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry></feed>