<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>the smaller things - personal</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://smallerthings.org/feeds/personal.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://smallerthings.org/</id><updated>2017-12-19T13:23:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Stumbling about in 2017</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/2017-stumbling-about.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-12-19T13:23:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-12-19T13:23:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2017-12-19:/2017-stumbling-about.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A rambling retrospective on a strange&amp;nbsp;year&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I severely underestminated the degree of befuddled I would experience following
the end of my PhD.
After spending over half a decade in the academic world, with half of that
fully intending to leave it for a career in industry, I found myself saddled
with a new crisis of identity I did not anticipate.
Despite all my preparation over the years, mentally and otherwise, I felt&amp;nbsp;adrift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s been a year since then, and only now do I feel like I&amp;#8217;m starting to find a
footing, something resembling solid earth.
The post-defense hangover is morphing into clarity of purpose, but I had to
stumble around the living room through an afternoon that lasted months for it
to happen.
I can&amp;#8217;t help but wonder if this is a common experience for others?
I would love to hear your thoughts if you (yes, you!) have gone through a
similar&amp;nbsp;period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve read in many places that people in academia exhibit a disproportionate
incidence of mental health disorders over the general population.
Whether this is due to the nature of the work, or due to the self-selection of
(often eccentric by nature) personalities it attracts, or both, is still an
open question.  But coming out of it, I learned there were many aspects of my
personality that were ill-suited to the world outside.  I also learned how
dependent I was on the environment for holding together whatever it was that
was there, and without that glue, I felt like my sense of self was falling into
pieces around&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2017 was a weird year.
This is an understatement for many reasons, and I&amp;#8217;m certain for many people
besides myself.
I sought to find identity in new relationships, new activities, new things.
In all these areas, in different ways, I failed.
And now, at the end of 2017, I stand at the precipice of a new year with much
of the old already cleared away.
I would have expected to be in a deep depression from this, but instead I feel
an internal peace and joy that I can&amp;#8217;t quite put words&amp;nbsp;to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve started the process of becoming my own friend.
I believe for a long time I&amp;#8217;ve avoided a friendship with myself, a real respect
and care for the person I&amp;#8217;m stuck with for life.
I did my damnedest to distract myself from his inadequacies, his failures, his
stupidity, often attempting to do so with more stupidity.
This of course didn&amp;#8217;t work.
But out of this mess I believe I&amp;#8217;ve found a new love, and his name is&amp;nbsp;David.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this was not the usual retrospective one might post on a personal blog.
It&amp;#8217;s also not something I&amp;#8217;d normally share, but frankly, I think it worth
sharing.
We all try to project an image of being &amp;#8220;put-together&amp;#8221; at all times, to keep up
appearances, to show maturity.
But we&amp;#8217;re not always put-together, and many of us may regularly be
high-functioning dysfunctionals in&amp;nbsp;life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m feeling well for 2018.
I look forward to spending it with all of you, another year around the star on
this lovely rock we call home.
Cheers to new&amp;nbsp;adventures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="life"></category><category term="purpose"></category><category term="social"></category></entry><entry><title>or/and</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/2016-or-and.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-04T14:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-09-04T14:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2016-09-04:/2016-or-and.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;often we think in &amp;#8216;or&amp;#8217;&lt;br&gt;
a choice between two or more&lt;br&gt;
when we could call it &amp;#8216;and&amp;#8217;&lt;br&gt;
and give ourselves the freedom to be all&lt;br&gt;
to enjoy all&lt;br&gt;
to have&amp;nbsp;all  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we dichotomize, split,&lt;br&gt;
we say &amp;#8220;him or her&amp;#8221;&lt;br&gt;
we say &amp;#8220;me or him&amp;#8221;&lt;br&gt;
we say there&amp;#8217;s a choice …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;often we think in &amp;#8216;or&amp;#8217;&lt;br&gt;
a choice between two or more&lt;br&gt;
when we could call it &amp;#8216;and&amp;#8217;&lt;br&gt;
and give ourselves the freedom to be all&lt;br&gt;
to enjoy all&lt;br&gt;
to have&amp;nbsp;all  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we dichotomize, split,&lt;br&gt;
we say &amp;#8220;him or her&amp;#8221;&lt;br&gt;
we say &amp;#8220;me or him&amp;#8221;&lt;br&gt;
we say there&amp;#8217;s a choice that must be&amp;nbsp;made  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but &amp;#8216;and&amp;#8217; is an open set of arms&lt;br&gt;
it invites, and accepts&lt;br&gt;
it understands&lt;br&gt;
&amp;#8216;or&amp;#8217; seeks to partition the world&lt;br&gt;
our lives, our bonds&lt;br&gt;
&amp;#8216;and&amp;#8217; says, let&amp;#8217;s connect&lt;br&gt;
let&amp;#8217;s be&amp;nbsp;whole  &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="relationships"></category><category term="choices"></category><category term="bonds"></category></entry><entry><title>2015: A retrospective</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/2016-retrospective-2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-01-17T17:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-01-17T17:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2016-01-17:/2016-retrospective-2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s been some time since I last posted, but that&amp;#8217;s not because I&amp;#8217;ve been
twiddling my thumbs. The year 2015 saw some big changes, and I wanted to take some
time to reflect and share on where we&amp;#8217;ve been (and where we&amp;#8217;re&amp;nbsp;going).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s been some time since I last posted, but that&amp;#8217;s not because I&amp;#8217;ve been
twiddling my thumbs. The year 2015 saw some big changes, and I wanted to take some
time to reflect and share on where we&amp;#8217;ve been (and where we&amp;#8217;re&amp;nbsp;going).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was about a year ago when I landed in Davis, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CA&lt;/span&gt;, to attend &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/2014-davis-swc-training.html"&gt;Titus Brown&amp;#8217;s
three-day Train-the-Trainers&lt;/a&gt; Software Carpentry instructor training. I met a
lot of folks that work in bioinformatics (not my field, but not far off), as
well as others involved in open science and open software. It was a
transformative experience, with the practical benefit that I was &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://smallerthings.org/2015-software-carpentry-instructor.html"&gt;offically able
to teach Software Carpentry workshops&lt;/a&gt; after finishing up some final requirements.
I went on to teach four in 2015, and a fifth just a week&amp;nbsp;ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;February saw &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://smallerthings.org/2015-biophysical-society-annual-meeting.html"&gt;my first trip to the Biophysical Society Annual Meeting&lt;/a&gt; with
research to present, having first gone in 2012 when I was just starting out.
I met many of Oliver&amp;#8217;s (my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PI&lt;/span&gt;) colleagues from Oxford and elsewhere, but spent
a good deal of the meeting finishing up some exciting results that had just
come in. The trouble with giving a talk is that you can work on it up until
you get to the stage&amp;#8230;so you&amp;nbsp;will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meeting was great, though shaping new results into a talk with short
turnaround was made possible by a software package I&amp;#8217;d been building called
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://smallerthings.org/2015-introducing-mdsynthesis.html"&gt;MDSynthesis&lt;/a&gt;, which that winter was finally in a state to be (exceptionally)
useful. It sped up my ability to slice, dice, and aggregate datasets from
myriad simulations I had performed, taking advantage of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pandas.pydata.org/"&gt;pandas&lt;/a&gt; DataFrames and
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hdfgroup.org/wp/2015/08/answering-biological-questions-using-hdf5-and-physics-based-simulation-data/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HDF5&lt;/span&gt; persistence&lt;/a&gt; to make fast exploration possible. I was on fire, and the
Baltimore cold couldn&amp;#8217;t put me&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I attended my first &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://smallerthings.org/2015-scipy.html"&gt;SciPy&lt;/a&gt; conference in July, where I presented MDSynthesis
as a poster. The conversations I had there influenced big changes in the package
that are still shaking out, one of which being the splitting out of the core
persistence functionality into a package called &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/datreant/datreant"&gt;datreant&lt;/a&gt;. A few other devs
from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mdanalysis.org/"&gt;MDAnalysis&lt;/a&gt; and I are now engaged with figuring out the future form of
this package, and the results are looking to be really quite&amp;nbsp;awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mdanalysis.org/"&gt;MDAnalysis&lt;/a&gt;, Google Code finally gasped its last breath, and this
forced the project to move elsewhere. Its new home became &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://github.com/mdanalysis"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, and,
perhaps unexpectedly, this became perhaps &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mdanalysis.org/2015/12/15/The_benefit_of_social_coding/"&gt;the best thing to happen to the
project in a long time&lt;/a&gt;. The great development tooling that GitHub provides
has catalyzed a flurry of new work, and has attracted new contributors,
including some that are now coredevs (yours truly&amp;nbsp;included).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The value GitHub added to MDAnalysis development spurred us to (finally) make a
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/Becksteinlab"&gt;Becksteinlab org&lt;/a&gt;, at which the open source projects incubated in our lab are
now hosted. I&amp;#8217;m proud to be in one of those &amp;#8220;with it&amp;#8221; labs, though a challenge
remains in getting busy lab members to actively work on projects that have a public
face and getting them in a useful state. I think this is a culture our lab
intends to encourage, but it&amp;#8217;s no secret that academia doesn&amp;#8217;t directly value
this kind of work today. But we&amp;#8217;re building for the world of&amp;nbsp;tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October I traveled to Germany (my first time in Europe) for the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.cecam.org/workshop-1214.html"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CECAM&lt;/span&gt;
biomolecular simulation workshop-of-workshops&lt;/a&gt; in Jülich. Despite wifi issues
in both the venue and the hotel, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/philipwfowler"&gt;Philip Fowler&lt;/a&gt; and I managed to start things
off with a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://philipwfowler.me/2015/10/23/software-carpentry-workshop-julich-12-13-october-2015/"&gt;Software Carpentry workshop&lt;/a&gt; that covered the Unix shell, Python,
and Git.  Oliver and I followed this with a (too short) &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/Becksteinlab/MDAnalysis-workshop"&gt;MDAnalysis tutorial&lt;/a&gt;,
doing things &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWC&lt;/span&gt;-style and live coding in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jupyter.org/"&gt;Jupyter notebook&lt;/a&gt; (using
pre-made notebooks as cheat-sheets rendered with nbviewer on my phone, of
course; we&amp;#8217;re not magicians). Both workshops were very well-received, with
people appreciating most the interactivity and the ability to play directly
with the library during the breakout components of the live&amp;nbsp;sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/richardjgowers"&gt;Richard Gowers&lt;/a&gt; visited our lab here in Arizona for a few weeks.
After treating him to some authentic &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://losdosmolinosphoenix.com/"&gt;New Mexican&lt;/a&gt; food (red or green?), he and I
got to work gutting the existing topology system of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mdanalysis.org/"&gt;MDAnalysis&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/MDAnalysis/mdanalysis/wiki/Issue363-Changes#search_word=topology"&gt;result&lt;/a&gt; is
more performant &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; more flexible (a rarity!), and should finally get merged
ahead of the long-sought 1.0 release. We&amp;#8217;re still not finished adapting everything
in the old topology scheme into the new one, but we&amp;#8217;re in the last 10% (where
90% of the time is&amp;nbsp;spent).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So where does that leave us in 2016? Well, this is my last year as a graduate
student, and I intend to defend my dissertation in the fall. I am in production
mode at the moment preparing new simulation systems to run over the coming months.
Once these are baking I&amp;#8217;ll be working on MDAnalysis and datreant/MDSynthesis
core components, while also preparing my analysis codebases for the data that
will be coming down the pipes. Writing (papers, dissertation) is also set to
begin in the next month or so. In February I&amp;#8217;ll be presenting work that should be
published soon at the upcoming &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.biophysics.org/2016meeting/Main/tabid/6230/Default.aspx"&gt;2016 Biophysical Society Annual Meeting&lt;/a&gt;.
There&amp;#8217;s no shortage of things to do.&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also hope to attend SciPy again this summer, and will be applying to job
opportunities throughout the year in preparation for 2017. If you&amp;#8217;re an employer,
or know of anything I might be interested in, by all means, &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:dotsdl&amp;#64;gmail.com"&gt;shoot me an email&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers to a new&amp;nbsp;year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="yearend"></category><category term="musings"></category></entry><entry><title>From Wordpress to Pelican</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/from-wordpress-to-pelican.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-12-26T22:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2014-12-26T22:15:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2014-12-26:/from-wordpress-to-pelican.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back in September I decided to begin sharing some of my thoughts on science,
software, and education by blogging regularly on my exploits. I&amp;#8217;d previously
built a website on top of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://wordpress.org/"&gt;Wordpress&lt;/a&gt; for
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sundial.physics.asu.edu"&gt;Sundial&lt;/a&gt;, so I decided to go with that
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CMS&lt;/span&gt;. I purchased a domain name through &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.godaddy.com/"&gt;GoDaddy …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back in September I decided to begin sharing some of my thoughts on science,
software, and education by blogging regularly on my exploits. I&amp;#8217;d previously
built a website on top of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://wordpress.org/"&gt;Wordpress&lt;/a&gt; for
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sundial.physics.asu.edu"&gt;Sundial&lt;/a&gt;, so I decided to go with that
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CMS&lt;/span&gt;. I purchased a domain name through &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.godaddy.com/"&gt;GoDaddy&lt;/a&gt;,
and out of convenience purchased Wordpress hosting through them as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wordpress is a fine &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CMS&lt;/span&gt;, but I despised writing in the built-in editor. I&amp;#8217;m
a vim nerd, and really wanted to write in plaintext in my editor of choice.
Also, I wanted to start sharing code snippets and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ipython.org/notebook.html"&gt;iPython notebooks&lt;/a&gt;, and Wordpress was appearing an awkward
choice at best for&amp;nbsp;this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;pelican&lt;/a&gt;, a static site generator
written in Python that uses ReStructuredText as the markup of choice
for articles. It took a little time to set up, but most of this was
spent trying to approximate my old blog&amp;#8217;s look by way of a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/dotsdl/pelican-bluemoon"&gt;custom theme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re interested in blogging with a statically-generated site through
pelican, start by installing the python module locally with&amp;nbsp;pip:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
pip install --user pelican
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then build a skeleton that includes everything you need to get started&amp;nbsp;with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
pelican-quickstart
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://docs.getpelican.com/"&gt;pelican docs&lt;/a&gt; have up-to-date information
on how to&amp;nbsp;proceed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since pelican generates static html files, they can be cheaply hosted. In fact,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; provides free page hosting via &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;. I created a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/dotsdl/dotsdl.github.io"&gt;repository for my site&lt;/a&gt; and edited the Makefile included
in my pelican project directory to point to it. This allows me to regenerate
and publish my static site&amp;nbsp;with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
make github
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn&amp;#8217;t get much easier. I&amp;#8217;m very&amp;nbsp;pleased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EDIT&lt;/span&gt;: I have added my &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/dotsdl/smallerthings"&gt;blog source to GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. Perhaps if you&amp;#8217;re having trouble
getting something working it will be of&amp;nbsp;help.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="blogging"></category><category term="pelican"></category><category term="wordpress"></category></entry><entry><title>Ahoy there!</title><link href="http://smallerthings.org/ahoy-there.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-09-22T00:02:00-07:00</published><updated>2014-09-22T00:02:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2014-09-22:/ahoy-there.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The last time I tried keeping a blog was when I was around 20 years old,
and the topics of the day were mainly of&amp;nbsp;interest to only 20-year-old
me. I was just coming out as gay, learning to deal with feelings I
didn&amp;#8217;t understand. I spent a lot …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The last time I tried keeping a blog was when I was around 20 years old,
and the topics of the day were mainly of&amp;nbsp;interest to only 20-year-old
me. I was just coming out as gay, learning to deal with feelings I
didn&amp;#8217;t understand. I spent a lot of time thinking about religion, and
plenty of time arguing about it with others. I didn&amp;#8217;t know much about
the world, but I was trying&amp;nbsp;learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m now 25, and in my fourth year of graduate school. I am invested in
my research (plenty to write about on that soon), and I am in a stable
and fulfilling relationship. Grad school started out (very) rough, but
I&amp;#8217;ve found my niche. I&amp;#8217;m generally&amp;nbsp;pleased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided it was appropriate to start sharing my thoughts and
experiences with others. It&amp;#8217;s not something I&amp;#8217;m used to, so it may take
a post or two before I&amp;#8217;ve found&amp;nbsp;my groove. Some posts will be about
science (both content and sociology thereof) and software development;
others will chronicle my teaching and thoughts on the state of
education. Yet others will be personal updates. I think there is space
for all of this&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plenty to&amp;nbsp;come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry></feed>