<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>the smaller things - personal</title><link href="https://smallerthings.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://smallerthings.org/feeds/personal.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://smallerthings.org/</id><updated>2024-12-01T22:00:00-07:00</updated><subtitle>states &amp; transitions</subtitle><entry><title>2024: State and Transition</title><link href="https://smallerthings.org/2024-state-and-transition.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-12-01T22:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-12-01T22:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2024-12-01:/2024-state-and-transition.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;life&amp;#8217;s second&amp;nbsp;act&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I feel I am entering my life&amp;#8217;s second&amp;nbsp;act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first act was about finding identity, self-esteem, my power.
It took me 35 years to do it, but it was a necessary path to arrive at where I am in time and space, among the confluence of forces that now accelerate me forward on the path&amp;nbsp;ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pains and pleasures of existence are necessary to shape us into the people we are meant to be.
What is up to us is how we respond to what we are presented with, giving intention to the choices and actions we take.
The most painful moments in my life are also the moments that drove the most growth, and I&amp;#8217;m thankful for the lessons they taught&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are also moments that are epochal, marking an inflection point in what would otherwise be inertial drifting.
I&amp;#8217;ve gathered the will, knowledge, and strength over the last several years to become what I need to be to have the impact I want on the world; what comes next is&amp;nbsp;execution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m standing at the top of one mountain; I&amp;#8217;ve learned all I can from it.
Higher ones extend before&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deep&amp;nbsp;breaths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="life"></category><category term="purpose"></category><category term="threads"></category></entry><entry><title>2020: State and Transition</title><link href="https://smallerthings.org/2020-state-and-transition.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-01-01T20:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-01-01T20:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2020-01-01:/2020-state-and-transition.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Where we&amp;#8217;ve been, where we are, where we&amp;#8217;re&amp;nbsp;going.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s been some time since I&amp;#8217;ve shared what I&amp;#8217;ve been up to on this blog.
Time for an update.
&lt;strong&gt;Strap yourself&amp;nbsp;in.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TLDR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: I&amp;#8217;ve developed a more stable motivational approach for myself, and this is the first iteration.
We&amp;#8217;re boldly going in a select few directions this year. Skip to the numbered lists for details without all the&amp;nbsp;context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Where we&amp;#8217;ve&amp;nbsp;been&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019 was a good year.
In roughly chronological order, here is a list of some&amp;nbsp;highlights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I snowboarded for the first time in over ten years&amp;#8230;twice.
   The first time was on New Year&amp;#8217;s Eve (technically 2018) in Flagstaff, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AZ&lt;/span&gt;.
   The second time was in the French Alps; I made it down my first black piste without any crazy&amp;nbsp;wipeouts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I made my first trip to Asia by way of Thailand.
   Although it&amp;#8217;s a pretty heavy tourist destination these days, I challenged myself by going it alone, with only a backpack as my companion.
   I had friends in Bangkok to show me around and spend time with, but I did quite a bit of the trip on my own.
   Also experienced my first food poisoning in a foreign country&amp;#8212;in the airport right before my flight&amp;nbsp;home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While on Kho Phi Phi, in the spirit of &lt;a href="https://andrewgreer.com/less/"&gt;Arthur Less&lt;/a&gt;, I took some time to reflect and write.
   My goal was to develop a 20-year plan for myself, starting at age 50 and working back to where I sit now, at age 30.
   I came away from that trip with a sense of direction and purpose I hadn&amp;#8217;t felt in a long time.
   More on that later in this&amp;nbsp;post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I turned 30.&amp;nbsp;:D&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I celebrated my fifth SciPy in Austin, and came away with some new means to execute on my 20-year plan in the near term.
   More on this&amp;nbsp;below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I traveled to Seattle to attend the International Space Elevator Consortium annual meeting.
   More on this&amp;nbsp;below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I took my Dad on his first trip outside of North America.
   We spent time in Paris, ate amazing food, and enjoyed so much of the culture the city has to offer.
   We made a pilgrimage to the American cemetery in Normandy as well; my Dad never thought he&amp;#8217;d be standing in it&amp;nbsp;himself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Last but certainly not least: I developed a closer connection with my partner, whose presence I&amp;#8217;m incredibly grateful for.
   He challenges me out of my comfort zone, and I do the same for him.
   He makes me a better version of myself with each passing day.
   It&amp;#8217;s the kind of relationship I&amp;#8217;ve always wanted, but thought I&amp;#8217;d never&amp;nbsp;find.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s certainly more to this list, but some things I cannot share&amp;#8230;yet.
Perhaps in a future&amp;nbsp;post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Where we&amp;nbsp;are&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019 is over.
2020 is about to&amp;nbsp;begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2019, I drafted a 20-year plan, starting at age 50 and working back to where I sit now, at age 30.
Although it has some specific milestones I&amp;#8217;m interested in hitting, emerging from this plan are three threads for my professional interests and efforts.
These&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Health and&amp;nbsp;Medicine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Molecules and&amp;nbsp;Materials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent 2019 laying out this plan and performing some of the groundwork for execution.
In 2020, I will begin execution in earnest, while continuing to clear the path forward for subsequent phases.
Although they appear unrelated, these threads possess some useful cross-synergies, which I plan to take advantage of to speed them all&amp;nbsp;along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Health and&amp;nbsp;Medicine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My efforts in thread (1), health and medicine, are tied together with my current employment.
I will be able to share more of this at a later time.
However, in vague terms, at this time I am focused on problems in operations and systems efficiencies.
More&amp;nbsp;soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Molecules and&amp;nbsp;Materials&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My central thread (2) is a continuation of the path I started on in my Ph.D work, but focused on pushing forward the state of the field using my atypical positioning.
As an independent researcher not seeking a faculty position in academia, I do not operate under the same incentive structures as many of my peers working in the field.
I can therefore do work that is of high-value but under-incentivized, such as software engineering, and I can do so without being as dependent on funding cycles and publication&amp;nbsp;demands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, my energy is going into the following&amp;nbsp;projects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://openforcefield.org/"&gt;Open Force Field Initiative&lt;/a&gt; - an effort that is poised to reshape the landscape of forcefield development, providing a needed refresh of the approaches we take developing this foundational layer of biomolecular simulation and enabling the rapid advancement of this layer into the&amp;nbsp;future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://qcarchive.molssi.org/"&gt;MolSSI Quantum Chemistry Archive&lt;/a&gt; - a key enabler of the Open Force Field Initiative, this effort is building a massive archive of quantum chemistry data, working to cover large swaths of chemical space with chemical property&amp;nbsp;calculations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/alchemistry/alchemlyb"&gt;alchemlyb&lt;/a&gt; - a library for performing (alchemical) free energy calculations using data from a variety of simulation (and experimental) sources, with an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; similar to that of &lt;a href="https://scikit-learn.org/"&gt;scikit-learn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These projects operate at the core of drug design and materials development, likely revealing opportunities in threads (1) and&amp;nbsp;(3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Space&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My last thread (3) is the most pie-in-the sky, literally and otherwise.
When I was a teenager, I developed an obsession with the concept of a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Space_elevator"&gt;space elevator&lt;/a&gt;.
It was the mid-2000s, and this idea was experiencing a surge of popular science interest from Brad Edwards&amp;#8217; 2003 book &lt;em&gt;The Space Elevator: A Revolutionary Earth-to-Space Transportation System&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like most things from childhood, when I went on to college, and subsequently grad school, other priorities demanded my attention.
I forgot about orbital elevators for about a decade.
But this year, an unlikely conversation with a friend brought these thoughts rushing back into the foreground.
Mental pathways I hadn&amp;#8217;t traversed in years were once more the center of my&amp;nbsp;attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thread, a ribbon to the stars, forms the pillar on which the other two derive meaning for me.
By the time I am 50 years old, I intend to be working full-time on an orbital elevator, assuming it is not realized already by then (in which case I may still be involved, or doing other&amp;nbsp;things).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two components needed for this effort that I intend to push&amp;nbsp;on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A manufacturing process for a tether with the required material properties has yet to be fully realized.
  There is excitement around graphene and boron nitride as candidate materials, as well as some manufacturing processes with real potential.
  &lt;a href="https://www.nationalgrapheneassociation.com/news/graphene-and-space-elevators-interview-with-adrian-nixon/"&gt;Adrian Nixon&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt; work and thoughts on this topic are particularly enticing.
  I want to assist with computational approaches where&amp;nbsp;feasible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simulation software for architectural design and failure analysis.
  This software may also evolve into key components to control systems for a real orbital elevator.
  The &lt;a href="https://isec.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/ISEC2017Study.pdf"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISEC&lt;/span&gt; 2017 Study&lt;/a&gt; lays out many of the high-value requirements of a simulation engine.
  I want to lead or contribute software engineering&amp;nbsp;effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Where we&amp;#8217;re&amp;nbsp;going&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passion and consistency are required.
I have not had either in the past several years as I wandered the desert, looking for meaningful things to direct my limited time and energy into.
This year made clear to me why I struggled for so long: I was too concerned with identifying things to do (&amp;#8220;what&amp;#8221;), but had no clear supporting reason for doing those things (&amp;#8220;why&amp;#8221;).
Without a visceral, motivating foundation, a list of things to do quickly becomes a list of chores, and without any other incentives (income, career progression, joy, etc.), they are deprioritized easily in the presence of other&amp;nbsp;options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My 20-year plan is a living document, and functions as a catalyst for progression and continued evolution.
It&amp;#8217;s less of a document and more of an ongoing process, which happens to have shape and content at each slice of time.
It&amp;#8217;s a wind for my sail, and it can change with time and circumstance, but its timescale of change is years, not days or weeks.
It is insensitive to swings in mood and short-term whims.
Its direction and consistency arise from deeper yearnings for meaning.
It doesn&amp;#8217;t matter so much where my boat ends up from this wind; what matters is that my boat is moving, and not in complete&amp;nbsp;circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The threads that emerge from this process speak to areas I have excitement about, are core to my personality.
I will be doing less travel this year, instead applying focused and sustained effort on them.
These threads map downward into specific goals and action.
Here is a list of concrete goals for this year, stated here for the&amp;nbsp;record:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-take the reigns of &lt;code&gt;alchemlyb&lt;/code&gt;, which has been a project in hibernation for some time.
   We will establish a regular release schedule, and I will make responding quickly and consistently on the issue tracker a personal&amp;nbsp;priority.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publish a &lt;a href="https://joss.theoj.org/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;JOSS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; article for &lt;code&gt;alchemlyb&lt;/code&gt;, promoting its purpose and use.
   This will provide a citeable reference for academics putting the library to&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborate on and contribute to this year&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISEC&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;study.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draft a computational material development pathway for an orbital elevator tether.
   This will require some correspondence with those working in this area, and at least one literature&amp;nbsp;review.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draft a design document for an orbital elevator simulation engine.
   This will map from the requirements listed in the &lt;a href="https://isec.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/ISEC2017Study.pdf"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISEC&lt;/span&gt; 2017 Study&lt;/a&gt;.
   We will use this document to guide implementation and recruit interested open source developers.
   This document will be developed in the&amp;nbsp;open.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draft the manuscript for the final project from my Ph.D. work.
   It&amp;#8217;s taken some time for that work to gestate, and there is now additional context to meaningfully place it in.
   This will be my first exercise in scientific publishing in many years, so it will&amp;nbsp;be&amp;#8230;interesting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will be pushing forward issues on the Open Force Field and QCArchive fronts as well, but those efforts are driven by others full time, with me operating in an at-will supporting role.
I also have goals aligning with thread (1), but these are tied to my employment and cannot be shared at this&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Some fun&amp;nbsp;distractions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I intend to focus my energies as much as possible into my threads this year, I also intend on the following&amp;nbsp;distractions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I plan to buy my first motorcycle this year, after some proper training to avoid injury or&amp;nbsp;death.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While it&amp;#8217;s still winter, I plan to snowboard at least once.
   It&amp;#8217;s too fun not to take the&amp;nbsp;opportunity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My partner and I are planning a trip to Portugal, probably in the fall.
   It will be our first international trip&amp;nbsp;together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once the Democratic presidential nominee is selected, I will participate as a volunteer in the campaign for Arizona with my&amp;nbsp;roommate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been working to build muscle mass since 2017, and have made significant progress since then.
   I will continue on this path with my partner&amp;#8217;s help.
   This is a key component to our lifestyle and our plans for the&amp;nbsp;future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I intend to be pretty ruthless about the distractions I allow into my headspace this year, so this list probably won&amp;#8217;t grow (much), barring major unexpected life&amp;nbsp;events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Sound&amp;nbsp;fun?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m always interested in meeting others whose interests align with mine.
If you&amp;#8217;re committed to action on threads similar to my own, please reach out.
I&amp;#8217;ve been fortunate to have many fruitful collaborations over the years, and they usually come&amp;nbsp;unexpectedly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="life"></category><category term="purpose"></category><category term="research"></category><category term="threads"></category></entry><entry><title>Stumbling about in 2017</title><link href="https://smallerthings.org/2017-stumbling-about.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-12-19T13:23:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-12-19T13:23:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2017-12-19:/2017-stumbling-about.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A rambling retrospective on a strange&amp;nbsp;year&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I severely underestimated the degree of befuddled I would experience following
the end of my PhD.
After spending over half a decade in the academic world, with half of that
fully intending to leave it for a career in industry, I found myself saddled
with a new crisis of identity I did not anticipate.
Despite all my preparation over the years, mentally and otherwise, I felt&amp;nbsp;adrift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s been a year since then, and only now do I feel like I&amp;#8217;m starting to find a
footing, something resembling solid earth.
The post-defense hangover is morphing into clarity of purpose, but I had to
stumble around the living room through an afternoon that lasted months for it
to happen.
I can&amp;#8217;t help but wonder if this is a common experience for others?
I would love to hear your thoughts if you (yes, you!) have gone through a
similar&amp;nbsp;period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve read in many places that people in academia exhibit a disproportionate
incidence of mental health disorders over the general population.
Whether this is due to the nature of the work, or due to the self-selection of
(often eccentric by nature) personalities it attracts, or both, is still an
open question.  But coming out of it, I learned there were many aspects of my
personality that were ill-suited to the world outside.  I also learned how
dependent I was on the environment for holding together whatever it was that
was there, and without that glue, I felt like my sense of self was falling into
pieces around&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2017 was a weird year.
This is an understatement for many reasons, and I&amp;#8217;m certain for many people
besides myself.
I sought to find identity in new relationships, new activities, new things.
In all these areas, in different ways, I failed.
And now, at the end of 2017, I stand at the precipice of a new year with much
of the old already cleared away.
I would have expected to be in a deep depression from this, but instead I feel
an internal peace and joy that I can&amp;#8217;t quite put words&amp;nbsp;to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve started the process of becoming my own friend.
I believe for a long time I&amp;#8217;ve avoided a friendship with myself, a real respect
and care for the person I&amp;#8217;m stuck with for life.
I did my damnedest to distract myself from his inadequacies, his failures, his
stupidity, often attempting to do so with more stupidity.
This of course didn&amp;#8217;t work.
But out of this mess I believe I&amp;#8217;ve found a new love, and his name is&amp;nbsp;David.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this was not the usual retrospective one might post on a personal blog.
It&amp;#8217;s also not something I&amp;#8217;d normally share, but frankly, I think it worth
sharing.
We all try to project an image of being &amp;#8220;put-together&amp;#8221; at all times, to keep up
appearances, to show maturity.
But we&amp;#8217;re not always put-together, and many of us may regularly be
high-functioning dysfunctionals in&amp;nbsp;life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m feeling well for 2018.
I look forward to spending it with all of you, another year around the star on
this lovely rock we call home.
Cheers to new&amp;nbsp;adventures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="life"></category><category term="purpose"></category><category term="social"></category></entry><entry><title>or/and</title><link href="https://smallerthings.org/2016-or-and.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-04T14:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-09-04T14:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2016-09-04:/2016-or-and.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;often we think in &amp;#8216;or&amp;#8217;&lt;br&gt;
a choice between two or more&lt;br&gt;
when we could call it &amp;#8216;and&amp;#8217;&lt;br&gt;
and give ourselves the freedom to be all&lt;br&gt;
to enjoy all&lt;br&gt;
to have&amp;nbsp;all  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we dichotomize, split,&lt;br&gt;
we say &amp;#8220;him or her&amp;#8221;&lt;br&gt;
we say &amp;#8220;me or him&amp;#8221;&lt;br&gt;
we say there&amp;#8217;s a choice …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;often we think in &amp;#8216;or&amp;#8217;&lt;br&gt;
a choice between two or more&lt;br&gt;
when we could call it &amp;#8216;and&amp;#8217;&lt;br&gt;
and give ourselves the freedom to be all&lt;br&gt;
to enjoy all&lt;br&gt;
to have&amp;nbsp;all  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we dichotomize, split,&lt;br&gt;
we say &amp;#8220;him or her&amp;#8221;&lt;br&gt;
we say &amp;#8220;me or him&amp;#8221;&lt;br&gt;
we say there&amp;#8217;s a choice that must be&amp;nbsp;made  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but &amp;#8216;and&amp;#8217; is an open set of arms&lt;br&gt;
it invites, and accepts&lt;br&gt;
it understands&lt;br&gt;
&amp;#8216;or&amp;#8217; seeks to partition the world&lt;br&gt;
our lives, our bonds&lt;br&gt;
&amp;#8216;and&amp;#8217; says, let&amp;#8217;s connect&lt;br&gt;
let&amp;#8217;s be&amp;nbsp;whole  &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="relationships"></category><category term="choices"></category><category term="bonds"></category></entry><entry><title>2015: A retrospective</title><link href="https://smallerthings.org/2016-retrospective-2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-01-17T17:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-01-17T17:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2016-01-17:/2016-retrospective-2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s been some time since I last posted, but that&amp;#8217;s not because I&amp;#8217;ve been
twiddling my thumbs. The year 2015 saw some big changes, and I wanted to take some
time to reflect and share on where we&amp;#8217;ve been (and where we&amp;#8217;re&amp;nbsp;going).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s been some time since I last posted, but that&amp;#8217;s not because I&amp;#8217;ve been
twiddling my thumbs. The year 2015 saw some big changes, and I wanted to take some
time to reflect and share on where we&amp;#8217;ve been (and where we&amp;#8217;re&amp;nbsp;going).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was about a year ago when I landed in Davis, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CA&lt;/span&gt;, to attend &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/2014-davis-swc-training.html"&gt;Titus Brown&amp;#8217;s
three-day Train-the-Trainers&lt;/a&gt; Software Carpentry instructor training. I met a
lot of folks that work in bioinformatics (not my field, but not far off), as
well as others involved in open science and open software. It was a
transformative experience, with the practical benefit that I was &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://smallerthings.org/2015-software-carpentry-instructor.html"&gt;offically able
to teach Software Carpentry workshops&lt;/a&gt; after finishing up some final requirements.
I went on to teach four in 2015, and a fifth just a week&amp;nbsp;ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;February saw &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://smallerthings.org/2015-biophysical-society-annual-meeting.html"&gt;my first trip to the Biophysical Society Annual Meeting&lt;/a&gt; with
research to present, having first gone in 2012 when I was just starting out.
I met many of Oliver&amp;#8217;s (my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PI&lt;/span&gt;) colleagues from Oxford and elsewhere, but spent
a good deal of the meeting finishing up some exciting results that had just
come in. The trouble with giving a talk is that you can work on it up until
you get to the stage&amp;#8230;so you&amp;nbsp;will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meeting was great, though shaping new results into a talk with short
turnaround was made possible by a software package I&amp;#8217;d been building called
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://smallerthings.org/2015-introducing-mdsynthesis.html"&gt;MDSynthesis&lt;/a&gt;, which that winter was finally in a state to be (exceptionally)
useful. It sped up my ability to slice, dice, and aggregate datasets from
myriad simulations I had performed, taking advantage of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pandas.pydata.org/"&gt;pandas&lt;/a&gt; DataFrames and
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hdfgroup.org/wp/2015/08/answering-biological-questions-using-hdf5-and-physics-based-simulation-data/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HDF5&lt;/span&gt; persistence&lt;/a&gt; to make fast exploration possible. I was on fire, and the
Baltimore cold couldn&amp;#8217;t put me&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I attended my first &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://smallerthings.org/2015-scipy.html"&gt;SciPy&lt;/a&gt; conference in July, where I presented MDSynthesis
as a poster. The conversations I had there influenced big changes in the package
that are still shaking out, one of which being the splitting out of the core
persistence functionality into a package called &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/datreant/datreant"&gt;datreant&lt;/a&gt;. A few other devs
from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mdanalysis.org/"&gt;MDAnalysis&lt;/a&gt; and I are now engaged with figuring out the future form of
this package, and the results are looking to be really quite&amp;nbsp;awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mdanalysis.org/"&gt;MDAnalysis&lt;/a&gt;, Google Code finally gasped its last breath, and this
forced the project to move elsewhere. Its new home became &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://github.com/mdanalysis"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, and,
perhaps unexpectedly, this became perhaps &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mdanalysis.org/2015/12/15/The_benefit_of_social_coding/"&gt;the best thing to happen to the
project in a long time&lt;/a&gt;. The great development tooling that GitHub provides
has catalyzed a flurry of new work, and has attracted new contributors,
including some that are now coredevs (yours truly&amp;nbsp;included).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The value GitHub added to MDAnalysis development spurred us to (finally) make a
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/Becksteinlab"&gt;Becksteinlab org&lt;/a&gt;, at which the open source projects incubated in our lab are
now hosted. I&amp;#8217;m proud to be in one of those &amp;#8220;with it&amp;#8221; labs, though a challenge
remains in getting busy lab members to actively work on projects that have a public
face and getting them in a useful state. I think this is a culture our lab
intends to encourage, but it&amp;#8217;s no secret that academia doesn&amp;#8217;t directly value
this kind of work today. But we&amp;#8217;re building for the world of&amp;nbsp;tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October I traveled to Germany (my first time in Europe) for the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.cecam.org/workshop-1214.html"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CECAM&lt;/span&gt;
biomolecular simulation workshop-of-workshops&lt;/a&gt; in Jülich. Despite wifi issues
in both the venue and the hotel, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/philipwfowler"&gt;Philip Fowler&lt;/a&gt; and I managed to start things
off with a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://philipwfowler.me/2015/10/23/software-carpentry-workshop-julich-12-13-october-2015/"&gt;Software Carpentry workshop&lt;/a&gt; that covered the Unix shell, Python,
and Git.  Oliver and I followed this with a (too short) &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/Becksteinlab/MDAnalysis-workshop"&gt;MDAnalysis tutorial&lt;/a&gt;,
doing things &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWC&lt;/span&gt;-style and live coding in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jupyter.org/"&gt;Jupyter notebook&lt;/a&gt; (using
pre-made notebooks as cheat-sheets rendered with nbviewer on my phone, of
course; we&amp;#8217;re not magicians). Both workshops were very well-received, with
people appreciating most the interactivity and the ability to play directly
with the library during the breakout components of the live&amp;nbsp;sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/richardjgowers"&gt;Richard Gowers&lt;/a&gt; visited our lab here in Arizona for a few weeks.
After treating him to some authentic &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://losdosmolinosphoenix.com/"&gt;New Mexican&lt;/a&gt; food (red or green?), he and I
got to work gutting the existing topology system of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mdanalysis.org/"&gt;MDAnalysis&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/MDAnalysis/mdanalysis/wiki/Issue363-Changes#search_word=topology"&gt;result&lt;/a&gt; is
more performant &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; more flexible (a rarity!), and should finally get merged
ahead of the long-sought 1.0 release. We&amp;#8217;re still not finished adapting everything
in the old topology scheme into the new one, but we&amp;#8217;re in the last 10% (where
90% of the time is&amp;nbsp;spent).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So where does that leave us in 2016? Well, this is my last year as a graduate
student, and I intend to defend my dissertation in the fall. I am in production
mode at the moment preparing new simulation systems to run over the coming months.
Once these are baking I&amp;#8217;ll be working on MDAnalysis and datreant/MDSynthesis
core components, while also preparing my analysis codebases for the data that
will be coming down the pipes. Writing (papers, dissertation) is also set to
begin in the next month or so. In February I&amp;#8217;ll be presenting work that should be
published soon at the upcoming &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.biophysics.org/2016meeting/Main/tabid/6230/Default.aspx"&gt;2016 Biophysical Society Annual Meeting&lt;/a&gt;.
There&amp;#8217;s no shortage of things to do.&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also hope to attend SciPy again this summer, and will be applying to job
opportunities throughout the year in preparation for 2017. If you&amp;#8217;re an employer,
or know of anything I might be interested in, by all means, &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:dotsdl&amp;#64;gmail.com"&gt;shoot me an email&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers to a new&amp;nbsp;year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="yearend"></category><category term="musings"></category></entry><entry><title>From Wordpress to Pelican</title><link href="https://smallerthings.org/from-wordpress-to-pelican.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-12-26T22:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2014-12-26T22:15:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2014-12-26:/from-wordpress-to-pelican.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back in September I decided to begin sharing some of my thoughts on science,
software, and education by blogging regularly on my exploits. I&amp;#8217;d previously
built a website on top of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://wordpress.org/"&gt;Wordpress&lt;/a&gt; for
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sundial.physics.asu.edu"&gt;Sundial&lt;/a&gt;, so I decided to go with that
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CMS&lt;/span&gt;. I purchased a domain name through &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.godaddy.com/"&gt;GoDaddy …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back in September I decided to begin sharing some of my thoughts on science,
software, and education by blogging regularly on my exploits. I&amp;#8217;d previously
built a website on top of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://wordpress.org/"&gt;Wordpress&lt;/a&gt; for
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sundial.physics.asu.edu"&gt;Sundial&lt;/a&gt;, so I decided to go with that
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CMS&lt;/span&gt;. I purchased a domain name through &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.godaddy.com/"&gt;GoDaddy&lt;/a&gt;,
and out of convenience purchased Wordpress hosting through them as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wordpress is a fine &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CMS&lt;/span&gt;, but I despised writing in the built-in editor. I&amp;#8217;m
a vim nerd, and really wanted to write in plaintext in my editor of choice.
Also, I wanted to start sharing code snippets and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ipython.org/notebook.html"&gt;iPython notebooks&lt;/a&gt;, and Wordpress was appearing an awkward
choice at best for&amp;nbsp;this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;pelican&lt;/a&gt;, a static site generator
written in Python that uses ReStructuredText as the markup of choice
for articles. It took a little time to set up, but most of this was
spent trying to approximate my old blog&amp;#8217;s look by way of a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/dotsdl/pelican-bluemoon"&gt;custom theme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re interested in blogging with a statically-generated site through
pelican, start by installing the python module locally with&amp;nbsp;pip:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
pip install --user pelican
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then build a skeleton that includes everything you need to get started&amp;nbsp;with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
pelican-quickstart
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://docs.getpelican.com/"&gt;pelican docs&lt;/a&gt; have up-to-date information
on how to&amp;nbsp;proceed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since pelican generates static html files, they can be cheaply hosted. In fact,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; provides free page hosting via &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;. I created a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/dotsdl/dotsdl.github.io"&gt;repository for my site&lt;/a&gt; and edited the Makefile included
in my pelican project directory to point to it. This allows me to regenerate
and publish my static site&amp;nbsp;with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
make github
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn&amp;#8217;t get much easier. I&amp;#8217;m very&amp;nbsp;pleased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EDIT&lt;/span&gt;: I have added my &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/dotsdl/smallerthings"&gt;blog source to GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. Perhaps if you&amp;#8217;re having trouble
getting something working it will be of&amp;nbsp;help.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="blogging"></category><category term="pelican"></category><category term="wordpress"></category></entry><entry><title>Ahoy there!</title><link href="https://smallerthings.org/ahoy-there.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-09-22T00:02:00-07:00</published><updated>2014-09-22T00:02:00-07:00</updated><author><name>dotsdl</name></author><id>tag:smallerthings.org,2014-09-22:/ahoy-there.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The last time I tried keeping a blog was when I was around 20 years old,
and the topics of the day were mainly of&amp;nbsp;interest to only 20-year-old
me. I was just coming out as gay, learning to deal with feelings I
didn&amp;#8217;t understand. I spent a lot …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The last time I tried keeping a blog was when I was around 20 years old,
and the topics of the day were mainly of&amp;nbsp;interest to only 20-year-old
me. I was just coming out as gay, learning to deal with feelings I
didn&amp;#8217;t understand. I spent a lot of time thinking about religion, and
plenty of time arguing about it with others. I didn&amp;#8217;t know much about
the world, but I was trying&amp;nbsp;learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m now 25, and in my fourth year of graduate school. I am invested in
my research (plenty to write about on that soon), and I am in a stable
and fulfilling relationship. Grad school started out (very) rough, but
I&amp;#8217;ve found my niche. I&amp;#8217;m generally&amp;nbsp;pleased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided it was appropriate to start sharing my thoughts and
experiences with others. It&amp;#8217;s not something I&amp;#8217;m used to, so it may take
a post or two before I&amp;#8217;ve found&amp;nbsp;my groove. Some posts will be about
science (both content and sociology thereof) and software development;
others will chronicle my teaching and thoughts on the state of
education. Yet others will be personal updates. I think there is space
for all of this&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plenty to&amp;nbsp;come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&amp;nbsp;david&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category></entry></feed>